Guide to the Peace TV Video Collection, 1978-1992 AIS.1993.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Peace TV Video Collection
1978-1992
1985-1989
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Peace TV (Firm)
AIS.1993.06
112 videos
These moving images were created by the non-profit organization, Peace TV, whose purpose was to provide viewers with alternative sources of in-depth news and information on peace and other social justice issues, as well as programing that they believed one would rarely see on the local commercial or public broadcast TV.
History
Peace TV was a non-profit organization that provided viewers with alternative sources of in-depth news and information on peace and social justice issues, as well as programing one would rarely see on local commercial or public broadcast TV. Produced by Richard Fishkin, it was created in 1988 as an alternative to what was called "War TV."
Acquisition Information
Gift of Rich Fishkin in 1993.
Previous Citation
Peace TV Video Collection, 1978-1992, AIS.1993.06, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains 112 Beta, Umatic and VHS videotapes of programs produced by Rich Fishkin of Peace TV on political, environmental, physical and spiritual health issues. Among these are world peace, U.S.-Soviet peace talks, U.S. military weaponry ("war toys"), the homeless and hungry, nuclear war, saving dolphins, big business and governmental corruption and conspiracies, Nicaragua, El Salvador, pro-union pieces, Iraq, ecology, Hiroshima. Also included is coverage of local events such as the Pittsburgh Press 1992 union rally and WTI reactor protests, as well as talks/lectures given by people such as Rev. D. Douglas Roth, Robert White, Helen Caldicott, Daniel Berrigan, Philip Agzzi and Brian Wilson. Some tapes are edited, others are not.
Related Material
Thomas Merton Center Records, 1962-2009, AIS.1982.19, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Arrangement
The collection was arranged and organized according to a list that was provided by Peace TV.
Environment; Television broadcasting -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Television programs -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Radicalism -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Television broadcasting of news -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Nuclear warfare; Television stations -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Homeless persons; Video recordings (physical artifacts); Big business; Videocassettes; Political corruption -- United States; United States -- Politics and government -- 1981-1989; Military weapons; Environmental quality -- United States; Labor unions -- Organizing; Ecology -- United States; Conservation of natural resources; Dolphins; Spiritual life; War; Health; Civil disobedience; Peace; Social action; Fishkin, Rich
- Political, I.
  - Ed Asner at the Rainbow Kitchen, May 25, 1990; Umatic (Box 1, Video 1-11)
    Scope and Content Notes
    Anne Feeney interviews Ed on politics, labor, arts and the American myth of liberty, justice and freedom of speech for all, "It is incumbent on every individual to ban together to prepare for the next election and to make the American myth a reality", said Asner, as he helped the Kitchen celebrate the opening of their new office, 30 min.
    Believed to have been filmed on Dec. 1, 1988.
  - Star Wars: Defense or Death Star, December 6, 1988; Umatic
    A presentation by Dr. Robert Bowman, President of the Institute for Space and Security Studies, at Peace Link's Fifth Anniversayr Dinner, Dr. Bowman explains why SDI is an offensive weapon and why it increases the chance of nuclear war! 75 min., believed to have been filmed on Nov. 18, 1988.
  - Thomas Merton Award: Daniel Berrigan, November 17, 1988; Umatic
    Daniel Berrigan reads his poetry at the Thomas Merton Award, 1988, Lynn Beckstrom sings the songs of Thomas Merton, Bonnie DiCarlo provides piano accompaniment, 55 min., Nov. 1988.
  - All Hallow's Eve Party, August 1988; Umatic
    A music video by Patti Heckart, includes interviews and the pouring of ashes on the steps of SEI by Vince Eirene to commemorate Hiroshima and Nagasaki, 12 min., August, 1988.
  - Cast Out the Demons of War: Halloween Party and Peace Parade, October 5, 1989; Umatic
    A Halloween demonstration by Women For Racial and Economic Equality, includes poetry by Jeffrey Richardson, music by Anne Feeney & Friends, mime by Noe Seager & friends, 55 min., believed to have been filmed on Oct. 30, 1988.
  - Rainbow Coalition, October 1988; VHS
    Congressman Walter Fauntroy gives an insightful an inspiring speech at the First Annual Rainbow Coalition Meeting, discusses the presidential election in the context of our countries current crises, 45 min., believed to have been filmed Oct. 1988.
  - Israeli Global Arms Connection, January 3, 1989; Umatic
    Jane Hunter, editor of Israeli Foreign Affairs, talks about Israeli foreign policy and its special relationship to the United States, at the Conference On Palestine, 55 min., believed to have been filmed on Oct. 15, 1988.
  - Brian Wilson, 1988; VHS
    Brian Wilson, recounts the events in his life that lead to the civil disobedience that cost him both legs as he tried to stop a munitions train with weapons for the Contras, powerful and inspiring, 80 min., 1988
  - Weapons Research at Carnegie Mellon, November 1, 1988; Umatic
    Includes a candlelight vigil and press conference the next day by Vincent Eirene, filmed on Oct. 20-21, 1988, 28 min
  - Sister City 5K Race/Walk in Peace, March 30, 1988; Umatic
    A fundraising and consciousness raising event to benefit the people of Nicaragua, 32 min., 1988.
  - Victory at Saltzburg, June 8, 1988; Umatic
    A rally and demonstration of civil disobedience by Arab American groups and local activists to stop Israel's use of tear gas on the West Bank and to stop the Trans-American Co. from selling it to the U.S. and Israel, 29 min., 1988.
  - Soviet American Peace Walk, June 8, 1988; Umatic (Box 2, Video 12-24)
    Music, dance and interviews in Scheneley Park, 34 mins., 1988.
  - Vincent Eirene, January 21, 1988; Umatic
    A conversation on the roots of civil disobedience, includes his C.D. at CMU's Sofware Engineering Institute, 55 min., filmed in 1988.
  - Peace of the Street: Father Hesburgh, December 11, 1987; Umatic
    Local peace activists protest the dominant role of the Pentagon in funding research at colleges and universities, 40% of Pentagon research is done by higher education, 70% of research at CMU is funded by the Pentagon, 54% of our tax dollar goes to the military, 2% goes for education!!!, 55 min., Dec. 11, 1987.
  - Soviet American Friendship Dance, 1988; Umatic
    At Penn Hills Volunteer Fire Dept, also includes Dr. Richard giving feedback to Rabbi Beerman, Los Angeles peace activist, 51 min., 1988.
  - Nuclear Winter, 1985; Umatic
    A lecture by Dr. Lewis Thomas, author of Life Of A Cell, 55 min., 1985.
  - John Stockwell Part 1, September 1986; VHS
    Former CIA agent (station chief in Angola), gives us a facinating glimpse of the real world of U.S. foreign policy, he urges each of us to do what we can for peace, part of the Great Peace March activities in Pittsburgh, 60 min., 1986.
  - John Stockwell Part 2, September 25, 1986; VHS
  - Great Peace March- Washington D.C., 1986; Umatic
    Washington, D.C., the end of an incredible journey, includes Ellie Smeal, Carl Sagan and several other inspiring speakers, 55 min., 1986.
  - War Toys Part 1, November 10, 1986; VHS
    A talk by JoAnn Sheehan, of the New England War Resisters Leauge, on the alarming militarism of toys and the incestuous relationship between manufacturers and children's TV producers, 45 min., 1986.
  - War Toys Part 2, November 10, 1986; VHS
  - Under the Mushroom Cloud, August 8, 1988; Umatic
    Includes Katho Kampfe's Rockwell and The Living Dead, a documentary of an August 6, street theater "die-in" on the steps of the USX/Rockwell Int. building in downtown Pittsburgh commemorating the dropping of the atomic bomb on Hiroshima/Nagasaki, also includes Quest For Peace interview with Helen Caldicott, anti-nuclear activist from Australia and author of Missle Envy, shares with us how she fought to make Australia a nuclear free zone, a very inspiring tape, 50 min., 1985.
  - Why are We Fighting Against the Hungry?, March 29, 1985; VHS
    A talk by Francis Moore Lappe, author of Diet For A Small Planet, explains how the U.S. uses food as a weapon of foreign policy and gives us an eye-opening account of life in Nicaragua, 80 min., March 29, 1985.
  - Why are We Fighting Against the Hungry, March 29, 1985; Umatic
  - No Victory without a Battle: Civil Disobedience at Carnegie Mellon, October 26, 1989; Umatic (Box 3, Video 25-33)
    Chronicles the adventures and philosophy of Pittsburgh peace activist Vince Eirene over a two year period, form 1987 to 1989, relates to his work to King and Gandhi, 55 min., October, 1989
  - No Victory without a Battle: Civil Disobedience at Carnegie Mellon (Master Edit), October 26, 1989; Umatic
  - Not in My Name, March 26, 1988; Umatic
    200 Pittsburghers march to demonstrate spirited opposition to the U.S. troop deployment in Honduras near the Nicaraguan border, good speeches by Paul Garver "we must answer unbroken chain of oppression with unbroken chain of solidarity", Jules Lobel "U.S. foreign policy of domination breaks international law", Joe Heckle "shut down the war college that graduates veterans" and Bob Gore " we must have jobs with peace, Blacks and Whites must unite to break the cycle of poverty and oppression perpetuated by our government", music by Collective Vision, 48 min.,
    possibly filmed on March 26, 1988
  - GE Boycott, June 1989; Umatic
    John Stewart exposes the insidious relationship between GE and the U.S. Dept. of Defense that allows GE to determine what kind of weapons we will build, explains why we must vote peace with our dollars and say not to five nuclear weapons a day, shot in front of the Pinellas Park neutron generator plant in the St. Petersburgh, Fl. area, 55 min., June, 1989.
  - Angela Davis Speaks for WREE, April 24, 1989; Umatic
    Women for Racial and Economic Equality, provides a unique historical perspective on the co-evolution of the women's movement and civil rights movement, "white women must be involved in the struggle against racism not just because they are morally opposed to it, not just because it is the right thing to do, but in order to further the struggle for women's equality", 55 min, April, 1989
  - The Shadow Government, May 24, 1988; Umatic
    The Shadow Government: The Men Behind the Iran/Contra Scandal, is a press conference by the Christic Institute, an interfaith law and policy center in Washington, D.C., about their investigation and lawsuit against the Private Enterprise, a group of private citizens, including many ex CIA covert operations agents, an organization that was used by the White House to carry on teh illegal war in Central America against wishes of Congress and the American people, Oliver North was the military liaison to the Private Enterprise, partners with drug smugglers for over 20 years, first in Southeast Asia and now in Central America. Dan Sheehan, chief council for Christic, " the American people know they haven't been told the truth, they are not going to acept the findings of the Iran/Contra Committee as anything but partial truth", 55 min., 1988
  - A Walking Prayer, May 20, 1988; Umatic
    Buddhist Monks, on their Walk For World Peace, come through Pittsburgh on their way from Chicago to New York City in support of the Thrid U.N. Session On Disarmament, walking is a form of prayer, "the chanting and drumming is a sacred prayer of faith in spiritual blessings of all humanity's ability to kindle a peaceful nature in all of our human family, people say this creates a vibration that awakens the inner heart", 10 min., May, 1988, this tape also includes a Quest For Peace interview with Elise Boulding, author of The Social System of the Planet Earth, "how can we build a new social order that doesn't need a military to settle differences, because there're just too dangerous", 30 min.
  - Weapons and Waste, June 12, 1989; Umatic
    Westinghouse. Weapons and Waste, Patti Heckart interviews Molly Rush and Johnathon Pressler of the River City Resistance Campaign about our country's nuclear fuel cycle, tying weapons and power plants together, Molly, "the plain situation is our government doesn't know what damage it's done to its own peole in the production of nuclear weapons, it doesn't know how to clean up the waste and it doesn't know how much money it will take to do that, current technologies can't handle the present waste problem", Johnathan, "Westinghouse undermines our democratic institutions by injecting huge amounts of money into the political process", 30 min., June, 1989, also on this tape a representative of Northwest Environmental Advocates discusses teh past and present nightmare at Handford, Washington, on the Columbia River, site of the largest nuclear waste adn processing facility, "the U.S. government has lied and covered up what goes on at Handford for forty years", 20 min., 1989.
  - El Salvador in Crises and El Salvador is Spanish for Viet Nam, April 10, 1989; Umatic
    A conversation with America Sosa, representative of Comadres - El Salvador, mothers of tortured and murdered political prisoners, shares her personal tragedy, her sons were tortured and imprisoned and her husband was tortured and killed, "solidarity with the American people stimulates and sparks us to move forward in our struggle", 15 min., March, 1989, also El Salvador in Crises, a heart-wrenching documentary of brutal repression, in the early '80s the U.S made El Salvador a scapegoat battlefield for fighting the expansion of communism, Senator Mark Hatfield, Republican of Oregon, "the ultimate human cost of this tragic conflict will be determined not only by decisions made in El Salvador but also those made in El Salvador but also those made in our own livingrooms and in the halls of Congress", a campesino told Dr. Charlie Clements, "you will never understand violence or non-violence until you understand the violence to the spirit that happens from watching your children die of malnutrition, that's what the issue is about in Central American today", produced by the Unitarian Universalist Service Committee, 30 min., 1988.
  - Robert White (ex-ambassador to El Salvador), October 1989; VHS (Box 4, Video 34-44)
    Robert White, ex-Ambassador to El Salvador, opens our eyes to our failed foreign policy in Central America, he shares his perspective on past events interprets the present and looks at future prospects in the context of national security, 40 min., October, 1989.
  - Larry Brown: Hunger in America, October 26, 1989; VHS
    Larry Brown, author of Hunger In America, addresses the Harvest Celebration Dinner sponsored by Just Harvest in support of World Hunger Month, "after six straight years of sustained economic growth in this country, more Americans are living in poverty today than any time in the previous decade", there can be no peace without econonmic justice, we can and must win the war on poverty and hunger, 30 min., Oct. 26, 1989
  - Rev. Dr. Wm Sloane Coffin: Can Pittsburgh Break Out of the Cold War?, February 13, 1989; Umatic
    A spirited and eloquent talk by Rev. Dr. William Sloane Coffin, President of SANE/FREEZE, his message in a nutshell is the same as Thomas Merton's, you can't have peae without social and ecological justice, "for the world to survive it must have truth, justice and peace",: one of the greatest problems in the U.S. is ignorance that stems from complacency", "we will always have low intensity conflicts as long as America has the right to decide who lives, who dies and who rules in other countries", 55 min., Feb. 6, 1989.
- Environmental, II.
  - The ECHO story, Umatic
    The ECHO Story, Seeds to Feed the World, a tour of the Educational Concerns for Hunger Organization experimental seed farm in North Fort Meyers, Fl. features shallow bed hydroponic gardening, an inspirational look at what a few committed people are doing to end world hunger, 55 min., Sept., 1989.
  - The Paper Bag Lady, October 17, 1988; Umatic
    Jeanne Bakelar, A Conversation With "The Paper Bag Lady" on solid waste crisis, conservation and the urgent need for nation-wide recycling programs, 55 min., 1988.
  - The Great American Meat Out, February 24, 1988; Umatic
    Great American Meat Out, a demonstration by Mobilization for Animals in front of Burger King and Wendy's, introduction by Rev. Rick, the Cybernetic Gospel Video Preacher, 49 mins., 1987.
  - TMI Train, October 16, 1986; Umatic
    Stop the TMI Train, two programs documenting the problems with transporting nuclear waste by rail, includes interviews with residents and politicians in Wilkinsburgh, a Pittsburgh City Council public hearing and a demonstration on the Bloomfield Bridge, 55 min., 1986-1987
  - Stop the TMI Train, 1986-1987; Master Edit Umatic
  - Heinz Kills Dolphins, September 6, 1989; Umatic
    Heinz Kills Dolphins, a demonstration at H.J. Heinz stockholders meeting protesting the way Heinz harvests tuna, Earth Firsters repel down the side of a building accross the street to unfurl a huge banner saying "Heinz Kills Dolphins", a classic case of corporate greed and blind market competition, 55 min., Sept. 6, 1989
  - Deep Ecology: D. Hanke, VHS
    Deep Ecology, a talk by David Hanke at a meeting of the Tampa Bay Greens, St. Petersburgh, Florida, discusses our species role in the environmental crises and suggests some thought provoking views on the Gaia theory, the earth is a giant organism, bio-regionalism and electoral politics, 30 min., 1989
  - Green Meeting, VHS
    Green Politics, Les Brunswick and PAul McIssac discuss the emergence of a new political party based on ecological principles, this program is just as, if not more, relevant today as is was in '85, 90 min., June 8, 1985
- Physical and Spiritual Health, III.
  - Harmonic Convergence Part 1, September 3, 1987; Umatic
    Harmonic Convergence, documents various Pittsburgh activities including music by Robbie Klein, a lecture by Michael East, Earth Dance by Mary Pat Mengato, ritual celebration by the Canay Indian Spiritual Circle and sunrise service by Jac Blackman, Three Rivers Church of Religious Science, 3 hrs., 1987.
  - Harmonic Convergence Part 2, September 9, 1987; Umatic
  - Harmonic Convergence Part 3, January 28, 1992; Umatic
  - A Conversation with Lao Russell, December 1, 1987; Umatic
    Embracing The Power Of Love, A Conversation With Lao Russell, director of the University of Science and Philosophy, Swannanoa, Va., Rene' Haldiman, of Rene's Crystals adn Books, interviews Lao Russell on her positive philosophy of life, 55 min., 1987.
  - Music for World Peace, 1987; VHS
    Maharishi's Festival Of Music For World Peace, Gandharvans playing the melodies of Gandharva Veda to create balance in Nature adn harmony in world consciousness, introduction by Andy LaRusso, 60 min., 1987
  - Rainbow Gathering, 1985; Umatic
    Rainbow Gathering, a documentary of one of the most intense cultural events happening today, 10,000 people gathered in the wilderness to celebrate life and love!, Allegheny National Forest, 55 min., July 4, 1986.
  - Viktoras Kulvinskas, Umatic
    Viktoras Kulvinskas, Co-Founder of HHI and author of Survival Into The 21st Century, is interviewed by Dr. Richard, good discussion of live food, natural hygiene and detoxification, 55 min., 1985.
  - Mind Walking, Umatic
    Mind Walking, documents a new powerful mediation technique using a Syncro-Energizer; light goggles, music, guided mediation and brain wave generator coordinated together to create a total environment of peace, 55 min., July, 1989.
  - Goin' Live, 1988; Umatic (Box 5, Video 45-53)
    Goin' Live, Rich Fishkin shows how to grow a variety of sprouts and makes a few of his favorite live food recipes, discussion of chlorophyll as blood cleanser, you are your own best doctor, live food as preventative medicine, join the real green revolution, 55 min., 1988
- Other, IV.
  - Save the Dolphins - Dolphin/Tuna Highlights, Umatic (Box 6, Video 54-62)
  - Political Communication in Revolutionary Nicaragua, Umatic
  - CMU Goes to War - Iraq Oil War, October 29, 1990; Umatic
  - Walk in Peace - Nicaragua, Umatic -SP
  - Homeless in Pittsburgh, July 10, 1990; Umatic
  - Reverend Roth, February 1, 1984; Umatic
  - Iris Kelso Interviews Jean Houston, Umatic
  - Hunger in America, December 1989; Umatic
  - Faces of War, Neighbor to Neighbor, and Nagasaki Demo, August 26, 1988; Umatic
  - Nowhere to Hind: Ramsey Clark in Iraq, April 11, 1991; Umatic (Box 7, Video 63-73)
  - You Are Now Under Arrest, 1991; Umatic
  - Fire and Water, August 26, 1992; Umatic
  - Peach Links: Are We Ready to Embrace the 21st Century, November 11, 1990; VHS
  - Housing Now!, August 19, 1931(?); Umatic
  - A City of Co-ops, Umatic
  - Helen Caldicott: Quest for Peace, Umatic
  - Dr. Bernard Lown: Physicians for Social Responsibility, December 6, 1990; Umatic
  - Math Sampler, December 1990; Umatic
  - Videogram from Tent City, Umatic
  - Electron and Proton Stemglass, Umatic
  - Barry Bluestare, Tri-State Conference, March 24, 1992; VHS (Box 8, Video 74-84)
  - CMU Found Guilty in a Time of War, Umatic
  - Mel King: At the Center, On the Edge, June 17, 1992; Umatic
  - Cispes:Paul Schwalb, August 12, 1990; VHS
  - ELO 33, Columbus WTI, October 22, 1991; VHS
  - WTI Protest, May 5, 1991; VHS
  - WTI Paul Connet, August 1991; VHS
  - Dynamic Duo: Electron and Proton, Scotch 1/2" Reel
  - Yosef Saloajee at Camp Solidarity North, June 15, 1990; Umatic
  - Overview of Nuclear Power, 1978; Umatic
  - Zen Ecology: Eybernetic Gosepel, Umatic
  - Zen Ecology Part 1, Master Edit (Box 9, Video 85-97)
  - Zen Ecology Part 3, Gerson Tape 1, April 13, 1982; Umatic
  - Zen Ecology, Gerson Tape 2, April 13, 1982; Umatic
  - Zen Ecology Part V, Mel Packer Tape 1, Umatic
  - Zen Ecology Part V, Mel Packer Tape 2, Umatic
  - Weiner Interviews Viktoras, Umatic
  - Fire and Water: Hiroshima 92, August 26, 1992; Umatic
  - Quest For Peace: Rabbi Beerman, Umatic
  - Philip Agee: Ex-CIA Agent Speaks Out, Umatic
  - El Salvador Demo, December 9, 1989; VHS
  - Pittsburgh Press Union Rally, July 28,1992; VHS
  - Maharishi's Festival of Music for World Peace, 1987; VHS
  - Earth Day 1990, VHS
  - Mitch Snyder Memorial, VHS (Box 10, Video 98-112)
  - Bread Puppet, VHS
  - Gail: Recipes for Life, May 21, 1983; Beta
  - Dr. Ann Slide Show Tape 1, Beta
  - Rapping with Fanchette Part 2, June 16, 1983; Beta
  - Jamie - Lecture, June 5, 1983; Beta
  - Union Yes: From Commonsberg to El Salvador, August 22, 1991; Umatic
  - Dr. Ann Tape 2, Beta
  - Dr. Ann Tape 3, Beta
  - Dr. Ann Tape 4, Beta
  - Rapping with Fanchette, June 15, 1989; Beta
  - HHI Tour, Beta
  - Jo Sessny, Beta
  - Kids -- Jay April: Kid and Parent, Beta
  - Jim Weiner: Viktoras, Beta